<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second part of The great question concerning things indifferent in religious vvorship briefly stated, and tendred to the consideration of all conscientious and sober men / by the same author.</title>
            <title>Great question concerning things indifferent in religious worship. Part 2</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22864</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12125443</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12125443</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29212)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 756:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second part of The great question concerning things indifferent in religious vvorship briefly stated, and tendred to the consideration of all conscientious and sober men / by the same author.</title>
                  <title>Great question concerning things indifferent in religious worship. Part 2</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: Edward Bagshaw.</note>
                  <note>The first part was published in 1660.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy.</term>
               <term>Rites and ceremonies.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54584:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The SECOND PART OF THE GREAT QUESTION CONCERNING THINGS INDIFFERENT <hi>IN</hi> Religious VVorſhip, Briefly Stated; And tendred to the Conſideration of all Conſcientious and Sober men. By the ſame Author.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi>Schiſm.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <hi>When either Falſe or uncertain Concluſions are obtruded for Truth, and Acts either unlawful, or miniſtring juſt ſcruple, are required of us to be performed; in theſe Caſes conſent were Conſpiracy, and open Conteſtation is not Faction or Schiſm, but due Chriſtian Animoſity.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54584:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54584:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE Chriſtian and Candid Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Buſineſs, not of <hi>Decent</hi> or <hi>Natural,</hi> but of <hi>Deviſed</hi> and <hi>Unneceſſary Ceremonies in the Worſhip of God,</hi> there are, Christian Reader, two Queſtions at this day more hotly diſputed then ever: The one is <hi>Whether they may lawfully be Impoſed?</hi> The other is, <hi>Whether when they are Impoſed, they may lawfully be obſerved?</hi> The firſt of theſe I have already handled; with what ſucceſs and ſatisfaction to others, becomes not me to determine. The Second is now the Subject of this preſent Diſcourſe; upon which indeed the whole ſtreſs of the Controverſie lies; and that becauſe of the Opinion of many Conſcientious and ſober men
<note n="a" place="margin">B. <hi>Morton.</hi> D. <hi>Burges.</hi> M. <hi>Sp. in.,</hi> &amp;c.</note>, who, though they are ready to acknowledge, that the Magiſtrate ought not to clog the Worſhip of God with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commanded Traditions and Inventions of his own, yet they conceive, that when ſuch things, as are not expreſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the Word of God, are Impoſed, they may and ought to be practiſed, rather then by the forbearance of them, men ſhould be forced to quit the exerciſe of their Miniſtry, which is ſo great a good, that they think it ought to be preſerved, though with the undergoing of ſome inconvenient Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54584:3"/>
            <p>To thoſe who either in their Writings do affirm, or by their practiſe do own this perſwaſion, I deſire to be very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but withal, I muſt take leave to profeſs, that I am not as yet ſatisfied, either with the Aſſertion, or with the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is brought to back it. For the Queſtion is not, Whether it be <hi>convenient</hi> or <hi>Inconvenient,</hi> but whether it be <hi>lawful</hi> or <hi>unlawful</hi>to comply or not? And therefore it ſhould firſt be enquired, <hi>quo jure,</hi> before we ask <hi>cui bono</hi>? that is, in all things which concern our Practiſe; we ſhould first be ſatisfied, that the thing we do is lawful, before we ſtate to our ſelves, that we have a good end in doing it: For ſince the leaſt evil may not be done to obtain the greateſt good, and ſince our Lord Chriſt hath ſufficient power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate his Goſpel without our ſin; it is to be feared, that at the laſt day he will not accept this as a ſufficient anſwer; that we mingled his Worſhip with the, otherwiſe unlawful, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of men, meerly to maintain our Liberty of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſince he can make our ſuffering for his Truth, to be as effectual a means for the Converſion of others, as our open and free declaringit. As the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſes, that <hi>his Bonds</hi> did beget many to the Faith of Chriſt. I wiſh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that too many do not indulge themſelves a dangerous Latitude, not ſo much to preſerve their <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their <hi>Maintenance,</hi> and ſo to their ſin of Compliance, aad a ſecret diſtrust of Gods Providence.</p>
            <p>But what others may be induced to do, concerns not me at all, who have nothing to do <hi>to judge anothers Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> but having my ſelf been frequently? importuned to conform, and that by perſons whom I very much reſpect and honour, I have adventured to publiſh my Reaſons, why for the preſent I cannot think it Lawful: Which is a work ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to cenſure and miſconſtruction, that I ſhould never have undertaken it, but that I would make it appear, it is not hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, but Conſcience, that hath guided me unto this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb facs="tcp:54584:3"/>And though it is poſſible I may be ſuſpected to favour the irregular Fancies of ſome, with whom every ſlight and trivial difference is a ſufficient ground of ſeparation; yet I can aſſure thee, Chriſtian Reader, I do ſo much abhor the Practiſes and Opinions of thoſe men, that though I may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the uſage of our <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> yet no occaſion ſhall make me forſake the <hi>Communion of our Church,</hi> whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, in the moſt material and diſputable Points of it, I have already aſſerted; and if I do not in all Particulars com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with her Diſcipline; it is not becauſe I would eclipſe her ſplendor, or leſſen her Authority; but becauſe I take ſome of the things Impoſed to be of that Nature, as no Power how great and lawful ſoever, can juſtifie and warrant the uſe of them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude therefore, with what I find in the <hi>Oxford Reaſons,</hi> excellently argued againſt Impoſing the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant: Thus have we,</hi> ſay they, <hi>clearly and freely repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented</hi> our preſent judgment, which, upon better Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in any particular, we ſhall be ready to rectifie. Only we deſire, it may be conſidered, that if any one fingle reaſon or ſcruple remain unſatisfied (though we ſhould receive ſatisfaction in all the reſt) the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence alſo would remain ſtill unſatisfied; and in that caſe, it can neither be reaſonable for them to preſs us, who cannot ſatisfie us; nor lawful for us, that cannot be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, to ſubmit unto the ſaid Covenant, <hi>This Paſſage,</hi> if in ſtead of the word <hi>Covenant,</hi> we read <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> contains as much as I have to ſay: And I am not without hope, that thoſe who were ſo ſcrupulous of being Impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>then,</hi> will be as tender of Impoſing <hi>now;</hi> ſince the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies</hi> in queſtion, are by many thought to be as contrary to the <hi>Law of God,</hi> as they had reaſon to think the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> was to the <hi>Law of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ch. Ch.</hi> 
                  <date>Sept. <hi>10. 1661.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Edward Bagſhaw.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:54584:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54584:4"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART Of the GREAT QUESTION Concerning INDIFFERENT THINGS IN RELIGIOUS WORSHIP, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Whether it be Lawful to ſubmit unto the Uſe and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of things, commonly ſuppoſed to be Indifferent, when they come to be Impoſed and made Neceſſary in Religious Worſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the righter Stating and clearer Underſtanding of this Queſtion, I ſuppoſe theſe two Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>Things commonly ſuppoſed to be Indifferent,</hi> I do not mean ſuch things as are purely, and in their own Nature <hi>Indifferent;</hi> ſuch are the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> of Religious Worſhip. Nor, 2. Such things, as in their own nature, though Indifferent, yet ſeem to have a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Aſpect and tendency unto that which is Natural Decency and Order, then otherwiſe; as, to <hi>ſtand or kneel, at time of Publick
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54584:5"/>Prayer,</hi> and the like: In both theſe Caſes, though perhaps the Magiſtrate doth ill to interpoſe his Command, becauſe things of a Religious Concernment belong not properly and immediatly to his Juriſdiction; yet I ſee not why his Command ſhould make us ſcruple or forbear the doing of them: For whatever, either in it ſelf, or in common eſtimation among ſober men, is more <hi>decent</hi> and <hi>comely,</hi> though it gaines no ſtrength from the Command Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it, yet there can no reaſon be given, why it ſhould loſe any. Therefore by <hi>Things Indifferent</hi> in the Queſtion, I mean ſuch things, as being conſidered at large, and diveſted from all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, may perhaps be done or not done, and that lawfully; yet <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> with reference to the power which impoſes, and to the end which continues them, it is queſtionable whether they be <hi>Indifferent</hi> or not; ſuch are, the <hi>Surplice in time of Publick Prayer, Muſick in Churches, Preſcribed Forms of Prayer, the Croſs in Baptiſm, Kneeling at the Sacrament, Bowing at the Name of Jeſus,</hi> and the like; which are not ſo purely <hi>Indifferent,</hi> but that they offend the <hi>Weak,</hi> who doubt; and cauſe many fierce and vehement Contentions, even amongſt the <hi>Learned,</hi> who diſpute, whether they be lawful or not: And about theſe things alone, do I deſire to be underſtood in my following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>Submitting,</hi> I do not mean, a being preſent at ſuch time and place, where theſe Rites are uſed, but actively concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to, and perſonally doing them our ſelves: For as Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> excellently obſerves, <hi>What if thoſe to whom the Execution of the Publick Service is committed, do ſomthing either unſeemly or ſuspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, or peradventure unlawful? What if the Garments they wear, be cenſured, nay indeed be ſuſpitious? What if Geſture or Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be uſed to the Altars, as now we have learned to ſpeak? What if the Homiliſt have preached, or delivered any Doctrine for truth, of which we are not well perſwaded? Yet for all this, we may not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate, except we be conſtrained perſonally to bear a part in them our ſelves.</hi> And therefore the Queſtion doth not ſo properly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the People, who, for ought I know, may be preſent where theſe <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are uſed,
<note place="margin">1 Kings. 19.</note> without being defiled by them, as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijah</hi> was a looker on upon <hi>Baals Prieſts;</hi> and the Apoſtle tels us, we <hi>may eat meat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Con. 8.</note> and therefore hear the Word, <hi>though in an Idols Temple.</hi> But I chiefly mean the Preachers and Miniſters of the Word, upon whoſe Perſonal Practiſe all theſe things are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54584:5"/>and this I hold utterly unlawful for them to ſubmit unto.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe the Magiſtrate hath no power to impoſe things doubtful and diſputable upon the Practiſe of any in the Service of God; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> and therefore it cannot be lawful for any, to obey him, when he ſo impoſes: For the clearing of which Reaſon, two things are to be explained.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Magiſtrate hath no Power to impoſe things doubtful and diſputable in the Service of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>if he doth impoſe, we cannot lawfully obey him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Aſſertion is this; That <hi>the Magiſtrate hath no Power to impoſe things doubtful and diſputable in the Service of God:</hi> And the Reaſon is clear, becauſe God hath given him no ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion: For ſince it is moſt Equal and Reaſonable, that God ſhould be the ſole Orderer of his own Worſhip, and if in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Will (which the Magiſtrate is as much bound to obey, as the meaneſt Chriſtian) God hath not authorized any to enforce upon the Practiſe of others, things which are of a doubtful and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputable nature; then cannot the Magiſtrate lawfully take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that power, becauſe in ſo doing, he goes beyond his Bounds, and exceeds thoſe Limits, which God hath ſet all that profeſs Faith in him, <hi>viz.</hi> of not <hi>being wiſe and holy above what is written.</hi> Beſides, our Saviour while he was upon Earth, though he had <hi>all Power committed to him,</hi> as Mediator, yet he neither exerciſed himſelf, nor intruſted to his Apoſtles ſuch Power, that they ſhould force or compell any to obey him, becauſe <hi>his Kingdom is not of this world, i. e.</hi> not to be acquired or enlarged by thoſe Arts and Policies which humane Princes uſe; but <hi>Converts</hi> only are his Subjects; and thoſe he alone owns for Members of his Church, whom Preaching and ſound Perſwaſion hath won over to him. And therefore it is very incongruous for the Magiſtrate, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to act for Chriſt, to take more upon him then Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did, and by enforcing things dubious, make Religion a very uneaſie and unpleaſant yoke, and thereby fright Conſcientious and Sober men from the Service of him, whoſe honour he would ſeem to promote; which is directly contrary, both to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Religion, and to the Ends of Chriſtian Government.</p>
            <p>Againſt this, in behalf of the Civil Magiſtrates Power, it is urged.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:54584:6"/>
            <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> That <hi>Jehoſaphat, Hezekiah,</hi> and other Kings of the <hi>Jews,</hi> are commended for repairing and beautifying the Temple and Worſhip of God; and likewiſe <hi>David</hi> made <hi>Muſical Inſtruments,</hi> appointed the <hi>Courſes of the Prieſts,</hi> preſcribed their <hi>Garments and manner of Service,</hi> none of which were provided for by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> from whence it followes, that Chriſtian Magiſtrates have ſtill the ſame power, which the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Princes had; that is, to regulate and order the outward Circumſtances of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, though over <hi>Subſtantials,</hi> and <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged they have no Power at all.</p>
            <p>But I Anſwer: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">Deut. 17.18, 19.</note> That whatever the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Princes did in regulating Gods Worſhip, they had a particular and expreſs Law, which did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act it from them; and which in all, even the ſmalleſt Punctilio's and Circumſtances, had ſo provided, that they could not fail of knowing their Duty; whereas Chriſtian Religion is in moſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of leſſer moment, more free and undetermined, and therefore there is not the ſame parity of Reaſon, that the example of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Princes then, ſhould be obligatory to our Magiſtrates now, becauſe the Law is altered, and that accurateneſs in ſmall things needs not ſo much be inſiſted on. For now the Magiſtrate moſt conſults Gods honour, and his own duty, if he leaves the Chriſtian Law as large as he found it; and doth not urge, either little, or much leſs doubtful things, becauſe God, in not requiring them, ſhews, that the preſſing them, will not be a work pleaſing or acceptable to him, becauſe it laies an Imputation upon his Wiſdom and Holineſs, as if he had not in his Word ſufficiently provided for his own Worſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And more particularly, to that Inſtance of <hi>David,</hi> I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That whatever <hi>David</hi> did in regulating the Service of God, in appointing <hi>Muſical Inſtruments, Prieſts Garments.</hi> and the like, he did it not by his Authority, as <hi>King;</hi> but by Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as a <hi>Prophet;</hi> as will appear from theſe Places of Scripture: One is, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 8.14. Where it is ſaid, that <hi>Solomon appointed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Order of David his Father, the Courſes of the Prieſts, to their Service, and the Levites to their Charges, to praiſe and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter before the Prieſts, as the duty of every day required: For ſo,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>David the man of God commanded.</hi> Where that Expreſſion, <hi>The man of God</hi> (which is a Name given only to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54584:6"/>extraordinarily inſpired, ſuch (were the Prophets of old) ſufficiently ſhews in what capacity <hi>David</hi> ordered theſe things; not barely as a King, but as a <hi>man of God, i. e.</hi> by God himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited and inſpired to do it. Again, when <hi>Hezekiah</hi> reſtored the Purity of Gods Worſhip, which his Father <hi>Ahaz</hi> had polluted, it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 29.25.</note> that <hi>He ſet the Levites in the Houſe of the Lord with Cymbals, with Pſalteries, and with Harps, according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of David, and of Gad the Kings Seer, and of Nathan the Prophet, For,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>ſo was Gods Commandment by the Prophets:</hi> Whence it plainly appears, that <hi>David</hi> did no more in theſe Particulars, then what God himſelf had by his Prophets commanded. And therefore when <hi>David</hi> gave to <hi>Solomon</hi> his Son the Pattern of Gods Houſe, and of all the Rooms and Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in it, it is ſaid to be, <hi>the pattern of all that he had by the spirit,</hi> among which things are reckoned,
<note place="margin">1 Chron. 28.12. V. 19.</note> 
               <hi>the Courſes of the Prieſts and of the Levites, and for all the work of the Service of the Houſe of the Lord:</hi> Of which the Text ſaies, <hi>All this, ſaid David, the Lord made me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand in Writing, by his hand upon me, even all the works of this Pattern.</hi> From whence it evidently follows, that not the leaſt Circumſtance which <hi>David</hi> then ordered, came from his own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or was eſtabliſhed barely by his Kingly Authority, but it did proceed from the infallible Directions of Gods Spirit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Magiſtrates cannot urge his Example, unleſs they will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend at leaſt to his Divine Aſſiſtance, and not <hi>Regal,</hi> but <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> Authority.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Since the Objecters allow that over <hi>Subſtantials,</hi> as for example, to make or command <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> Magiſtrates have no power; methinks it demonſtrably followes from their own Conceſſions, that over <hi>Circumstantials</hi> they have much leſs: Since <hi>Subſtantials</hi> concern the Eſſence of Worſhip, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may ſeem to be a juſt ground for Impoſition; upon which, the Apoſtles found the Equity of their <hi>Canon,</hi> about forbidding <hi>things ſtrangled, Blood</hi> and <hi>Fornication,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 15.28.</note> becauſe they were <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>things very neceſsary;</hi> but <hi>Circumſtantials</hi> may very well be omitted, without any prejudice either to Gods Worſhip, or to the Magiſtrates Power; and the very needleſſeneſs and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of them, may ſeem juſtly enough, to make it unlawful to impoſe them: For if in general, the Magiſtrate hath nothing to do, whether I am a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> or not, ſince as a <hi>man,</hi> I have a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to his Protection: then ſure, when I acknowledge my ſelf a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54584:7"/>
               <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> in what kind of <hi>Habit, Poſture,</hi> or <hi>Words,</hi> I will wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, the Magiſtrate hath much leſs to do, becauſe <hi>Charity, Forbearance, Doing as he would be done by, not to lay a ſtumbling Block before his Brother,</hi> and the like, are as much Parts of the Chriſtian Magiſtrates Duty, as Obedience to the Magiſtrate in all lawful, and therefore not diſputable things, is the duty of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Subject.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> It is objected again, That there are many Prophecies in Scripture, that Magiſtrates ſhould own and defend Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.23.</note> and in particular, that <hi>Kings ſhould be Nurſing Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Queens Nurſing Mothers to the Church;</hi> and therefore certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they may employ their Authority for the beautifying and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning it in all ſuch outward Circumſtances of Worſhip, as meerly appertain to Decency and Order.</p>
            <p>But I Anſwer: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. There are indeed many Prophecies in Scripture, that Kings and Inferiour Magiſtrates ſhall ſubmit to the Faith of Chriſt; yet it doth not follow, that therefore they are to take upon them to model and regulate any part of his Worſhip.
<note place="margin">C. 7.18.</note> For as in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion about the <hi>Reign of the Saints,</hi> it is clear from Scripture, that a time will come when the Saints ſhall rule the world, as in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, The Saints of the Moſt High ſhall take the Kingdom, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the Kingdom for ever, even for ever and ever:</hi> Yet it doth not follow, that therefore they ought to take Arms, and by violence poſſeſſe themſelves of an Earthly Kingdom, becauſe this contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts ſo many other places, wherein <hi>Patience, Self-denial,</hi> and <hi>Waiting upon God,</hi> is enjoyned them. So in this caſe, there is a vaſt difference between a Magiſtrates becoming Chriſtian, and his medling with Preſcribing Forms of Chriſtian Worſhip, which no Prophecy did ever mention: Nay on the contrary, in ſtead of foretelling any ſuch Imperious and authoritative Rule of Princes, in Religious matters, the Scripture mentions their lowly and humble deportment; as in <hi>Davids</hi> Prophecy concerning the <hi>Meſſiah: All Kings ſhall fall down before him, all Nations ſhall ſerve him.</hi> And in <hi>Iſaiah, Kings ſhall ſee and ariſe; Princes alſo ſhall worſhip.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 72.11. Iſa.49 7.</note> Nay in that very place, where there is mention of <hi>Kings being Nurſing Fathers,</hi> it is added, <hi>they ſhall lie down to thee with their Face towards the earth, they ſhall lick the duſt of thy Feet:</hi> Which places do rather argue the Magiſtrates awful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54584:7"/>of, and reſpectful ſubmiſſion to the Church of Chriſt, then their exerciſing Authority over it. At leaſt thus much may be evinced, that, though Magiſtrates loſe no power by becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians, yet they gain none, but in every thing are to act as Servants to the Law of Chriſt; from which, as nothing may be taken, ſo to it nothing ought to be added; no, though it may be patronized under the names of <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order;</hi> which if we make to ſignifie, not <hi>Natural,</hi> but <hi>Deviſed</hi> and Fancied <hi>Order,</hi> it is that which all Superſtitions plead, to defend their unwarranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Traditions and Inventions by. And therefore to purſue the <hi>Simile</hi> a little farther, it were to be wiſhed, that <hi>Kings</hi> would ſo far prove <hi>Nurſing-Fathers,</hi> as to uſe their Chriſtian Subjects in this particular, as <hi>Nurſes</hi> do their Children, <hi>i. e.</hi> only to put into their Mouths, that which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> cals <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>Reaſonable</hi> and <hi>ſincere</hi> or <hi>unmingled Milk, i. e.</hi> only Gods Word in its Native Purity, without being ſowred by the Harſhneſs of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, or corrupted, rather then ſweetned, by the undue mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Humane Fancies and Imaginations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The beſt way for Chriſtian Magiſtrates to advance and beautifie Religion, is not by the Prodigality of their Purſes, in <hi>stately Structures, Choyce Muſick, Curious Pictures,</hi> and the like, wherein Superſtition will be ſure to out-do them; or by the Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Rigour of their Laws in ſmall things, but in the Piety of their Lives, and ſtrictneſs of their Civil Government. For let Magiſtrates once cleanſe the Soyl of Humane Nature, by making ſharp and wholſom Laws againſt Vice and Immorality, and then weed it, by impartial puniſhing of <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi> and other Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which the Apoſtle cals <hi>Works of the Fleſh;</hi> then Religion will make its own way into mens hearts, and produce an outward Compoſure in Service, ſutable to its own inward Worth and Excellence: Whereas the Magiſtrates medling with <hi>Outward Forms,</hi> begets only a Face of Religion, which is ſo much the more loathſom, in that it is uſed commonly as a Cover, to hide many foul Enormities, which without that Mask, no ſober Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate could have the heart to tolerate. I conclude therefore ſince, 1. God never gave. 2. Chriſt never exerciſed. 3. The Examples of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Princes, nor Scripture Propheſies do war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſuch an impoſing Power, eſpecially in things doubtful, as ſome contend for, it follows, that the Civil Magiſtrate hath no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54584:8"/>ſuch power, and ought not to take it upon him: Which was my firſt Aſſertion.</p>
            <p>The Second Aſſertion was this, That <hi>if the Magistrate doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe things doubtful, we cannot lawfully obey him:</hi> And the Reaſon is clear, from what is already argued: For no man can lawfully do any thing in the Worſhip of God, but what he is ſatisfied he might do, whether it were by men commanded or not; therefore he that hath no other warrant for his doing any thing, then the Command of the Magiſtrate, when it is clear the Magiſtrate hath no Power to command him, muſt needs ſin in what he does: And that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe thereby he viſibly diſowns, and detracts from Gods Soveraignty, who is ſole Lord of the Conſcience, whoſe Honour is then given to another, when by our ſubmitting to them, we ſeem in fact at leaſt, to acknowledge, that they have Power to impoſe: For in the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by an Overt Act, to own and countenance the Juriſdiction and Authority of another, this is to leſſen Chriſts Legiſlative Power, and to make <hi>Two Heads</hi> of the Church, a <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Inviſible,</hi> or a <hi>Political</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> one, which is a diſtinction that the Scripture knows not; and only the <hi>Popiſh,</hi> that is the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Church makes uſe of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe by obeying what is in it ſelf doubtful, and in the Impoſer unlawful, we ſhall conſent to, and approve the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſin, and ſo harden him to continue more fierce and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory in it. Now if it be a Rule in general, that we <hi>ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our Brother, and not to ſuffer ſin upon him,</hi> much leſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<note place="margin">Lev. 19.</note> and to partake with him in it: How much more is it our duty, to prevent, ſo far as we can, any ſin in our Magiſtrate, (whoſe happineſs we are bound in eſpecial manner to procure and pray for) and this muſt be done, by our modeſt and humble, but yet reſolute and conſtant refuſing to obey his Impoſitions; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are ſo to proceed, as to evidence both by our Language, and Actions, that it is not Peeviſhneſs or Petulancy, much leſs a diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient and contradicting humour, which puts us upon it, but meerly Conſcience of our Duty, both to God and Him; namely, becauſe the Magiſtrate, as to theſe matters, is not in Gods ſtead, God not having committed unto Chriſtian Magiſtrates, but unto his Son, the Government of his Church, and that in the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54584:8"/>Policy, as well as in the Inward Purity of it: For where the inward Purity is not wrought, there outward Conformity is not a ſerving God; but men, and proves a Service, which as God requires not, ſo neither will he at all accept. And therefore ſince even the higheſt Magiſtrates on earth are accountable to God, who hates Oppreſſion, under pretence of advancing Piety; this, as it ought to make all Magiſtrates afraid how they meddle with impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, without any warrant, ſo it ought to make us wary too, leſt by active ſubmitting, we do abet and own their ſin, and ſo become Parties in the Tranſgreſſion; There being but little difference, in the ſight of God, between him that commands a doubtful thing, and him that doth it, upon no better argument, then becauſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who had no power, commanded it: For in that, or in no caſe, God cals for <hi>Suffering,</hi> and not for <hi>Submitting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He that obeyes in ſuch a caſe, muſt needs ſin, becauſe he cannot act in <hi>Faith, i. e.</hi> in a ſound and thorow, Perſwaſion, that it is lawful for him to obey. For ſince no Concluſion can have in it greater certainty then the Premiſes which infer it, I would fain know, how it is poſſible for him to have any clear ſatisfaction, who thus argues.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The thing commanded, as for example, the <hi>Croſs in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> is in its own nature very diſputable, whether it be Lawful or not?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Magiſtrate who commands it, hath no power to do it, and therefore ſins in enjoyning; muſt not then the Inference be, therefore I ſhall ſin in obeying him, ſince his Command, when he wants Power, can never make a doubtful thing warrantable or ſafe to a doubting Conſcience. From all which, it followes, that if it be unlawful to command a thing doubtful in Religious Worſhip, it is equally unlawful to obey it; which is the ſumme of my Firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
            <p>My Second Reaſon ſhall be taken from the Neceſſity and Nature of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty;</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> which as it conſiſts eſpecially in the free uſe of Indifferent, or Forbearance of doubtful things, ſo are we bound entirely to preſerve it. To clear up which, we muſt conſider, that the whole ſtream of the Goſpel, in reference to theſe outward things, doth run in ſuch Expreſſions as theſe; <hi>If you be my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>you ſhall know the Truth,
<note place="margin">John 8.31. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> and the Truth ſhall ſet you free.</hi> And again, <hi>If the Son ſhall make you free, you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54584:9"/>ſhall be free indeed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.1. V. 13. James 1.25. &amp; 2.12.</note> So the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Stand faſt in the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wherewith Chriſt hath made you free.</hi> And again, <hi>Brethren, you have been called unto Liberty,</hi> So <hi>James</hi> cals the Goſpel the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Law of Liberty:</hi> and, <hi>ſo ſpeak,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and ſo do, as thoſe that ſhall be judged by the Law of Liberty.</hi> All which places, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, to the ſame purpoſe, do evince thus much, that it is not a thing meerly arbitrary, and at our pleaſure, whether we will preſerve our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> or not; but we are ſtrictly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to do it: and the ſame obedience which we owe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Divine Precepts, we are obliged to pay unto this, becauſe it is dictated by the ſame Spirit. Now ſince this Liberty, as it is mentioned by our Saviour and his Apoſtles, is only to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in things of Religious Concernment (for as to Civil mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, no doubt, the ſtricteſt Obedience to the Magiſtrates Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, is our Duty) it follows therefore, that when once things, otherwiſe perhaps <hi>Indifferent,</hi> yet indeed <hi>Doubtful,</hi> come to be made neceſſary, and forced upon our practiſe, we are then bound by a meek and Chriſtian, but yet magnanimous Refuſal, to aſſert our Freedom, and not ſuffer our ſelves to be entangled by a <hi>Yoke of Bondage,</hi> which is ſo much the more heavy and galling, becauſe it is confeſſedly needleſſe, and hath no holier end to rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it, then meerly an undue will of the Impoſer; which if we obey,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.23.</note> we then become <hi>Servants of men,</hi> and cowardly deſert that Freedom which Chriſt came to purchaſe for us: which is quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary both to the Command &amp; Practiſe of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who though he held <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> in ſome caſes to be Indifferent, and accordingly uſed it; yet when once <hi>Falſe Brethren came to ſpy out their Liberty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> and by their ſubtil Diſcourſes <hi>ſought to bring them into Bondage, Paul</hi> would not yield to them in the leaſt, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly oppoſed the Inſinuations of thoſe crafty men (with whom no doubt, Arguments from <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> were not wanting) that ſo he might tranſmit the <hi>Truth, i. e.</hi> the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel unto his Followers: And for his own, both Judgment and Practiſe, he gives this General Rule, <hi>All things, i. e.</hi> which are not forbidden by God, <hi>are Lawful,</hi> but, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. I will not be domineer'd over by any,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.12.</note> or, <hi>I will not ſuffer any to exerciſe Authority over me,</hi> as that I ſhould upon his Imperious and unlawful Command, forbear the free uſe of that which the Lord hath left free unto me.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:54584:9"/>
            <p>Againſt this it is Objected, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> 
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> ſpeaks only of <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> and <hi>Jewiſh Ceremonies;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Liberty</hi> he mentions, muſt only be underſtood in reference to them, which all acknowledge to be aboliſhed, and without ſin, cannot be revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but this doth not concern other <hi>Chriſtian Rites,</hi> which are introduced, as by another power, ſo upon another Score, <hi>ſc.</hi> not as Parts of Religion, but as Circumſtances of meer <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order.</hi> But I Anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth not ſo confine his Diſcourſe to <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,</hi> but that in other places he extends it to <hi>Meats and Drinks,</hi> to <hi>Obſervation of Dayes,</hi> and ſuch like, which are much more indifferent, then thoſe now conteſted about: Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which, the Apoſtles Aſſertion is, <hi>That he would not be brought into bondage by any,</hi> but be left as free in the uſe or forbearance of them, as the Laws of Charity would permit. And therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Apoſtle ſaies, though properly and immediatly it relates only to <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cuſtoms, yet ſince his words are general and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, they muſt be underſtood equally to concern all things, that are of a like, and much more thoſe that are of a more doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though the Apoſtle did ſpeak only of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Legal Rites,</hi> yet the very ſame Reaſon which ſerved to take them away, may eaſily be improved, to keep back any other from being either impoſed or obſerved in their room. For, 1. Since God himſelf was the immediate Author of all <hi>Moſaical Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</hi> And 2. Since they were afterwards aboliſhed, not becauſe they were ſinful, but becauſe they were <hi>unprofitable;</hi> not becauſe they were inconſiſtent with Salvation, but becauſe they did not ſufficiently promote it, as the Apoſtle witneſſes: <hi>There is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.18, 19.</note> ſaith he, <hi>a diſanulling of the Commandment going before, for the weakneſs and unprofitableneſſe thereof; for the Law, i. e.</hi> of Ceremonies, <hi>made nothing perfect:</hi> Then it followes, that things, 1. Which have not the ſame Divine warrant and Preſcription. And 2. Which are equally, if not more unprofitable, as to what concernes the Conſcience, ought not to be introduced or practiſed; for elſe we ſhould be very little Gainers, if being ſet free from Gods, we might be made ſubject to mans Law, and if in ſtead of <hi>Divine,</hi> we might own and practiſe <hi>Humane Impoſitions:</hi> This would not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54584:10"/>eaſe our Yoke, but only alter it, nay make it much more inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table then the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Burden was: For they, in what they did, obeyed a Righteous and Infallible God, and therefore were ſure, they could not erre: But we muſt obey the Arbitrary Fancies of Unrighteous, and Fallible men, concerning whoſe Authority in impoſing, or the Uſefulneſſe of the things which they impoſe, we can never be ſatisfied; ſince they ſeem, not only to go beyond their bounds, but likewiſe by enjoyning ſuch poor things, to play with, rather then to adorn Religion, and in ſtead of conſulting Gods Honour, to provide only Traps and Snares for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious and ſoberly diſſenting Brethren.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is objected again, That the Church was not in the ſame condition in the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> time, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> that now it is in; for then there was no Civil Magiſtrate that did ſo far countenance Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, as to interpoſe and meddle with it, and therefore none could enjoyn thoſe things, in the uſe whereof <hi>Paul</hi> bids them be free; but now the ſtate of things is altered: For Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates have taken upon them the care of Religion, unto whoſe Injunctions we are to yield obedience, according to that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Let every Soul be Subject to the Higher Powers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 1. It is aſſumed <hi>gratis,</hi> and without the leaſt pretence of Proof, that the Chriſtian Magiſtrate hath any thing to do to impoſe in things of Religion: For which, I might bring many Sentences out of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>Lactanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who affirm the ſame: but the thing is clear; For Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is properly and adequately concerned only in Civil things; but Religious matters belong only to him that is Inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and Lord of the Conſcience; and therefore that Text, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> is in this debate imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently alledged; ſince it is evident, that the Apoſtle wrote it, with reference to <hi>Nero,</hi> who was then Emperour, and certainly did very little trouble himſelf with things of Religion, except it were to perſecute it; and even then when the Magiſtrate doth ſo, I acknowledge that we are to <hi>be ſubject to, i. e.</hi> not to reſiſt him; Nay, further, it followes from the Text, that ſhould our Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates become, what they then were, <hi>Heathen</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> yet in all Civil Matters, we were bound to obey them; which I am ready to aſſert againſt all, whether <hi>Papal</hi> or other Encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But that the Magiſtrate either hath power to preſcribe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54584:10"/>Religious Rites, or that if he doth preſcribe, we ought to ſubmit to him, neither that, nor any other Text of Scripture doth evince, as I have already demonſtrated.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I deny, that any upon Earth, now hath greater power to impoſe upon the Church, then thoſe had in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>'s time. For I take it for granted, that <hi>Peter</hi> was, if not the greateſt, yet one of the greateſt Perſons, that ever was ſince our Saviours time, and yet when he, by his ſuſpitious and inconſtant carriage, gave occaſion to the Gentiles, to think,
<note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> that the <hi>Jewiſh Rites</hi> ought ſtill to be continued, <hi>Paul</hi> openly reproves him, in theſe words, <hi>Why compelleſt thou the Gentiles to live as do the Jews? i. e.</hi> Why doſt thou ſeem to lay a conſtraint upon them, and by the Authority of thy example, induce them to believe, that thoſe Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies are ſtill to be practiſed? From whence I infer, that if in one who was ſo great an Apoſtle, <hi>Paul</hi> would not brook the leaſt ſcruple of carriage, which might ſeem to abate and leſſen the extent of Chriſtian Liberty, then it follows.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That no Magiſtrate can lawfully take upon him that power, ſince the greateſt Magiſtrate on Earth, in things appertaining to Divine Worſhip, is much inferiour to <hi>Peter,</hi> both for Knowledge and Authority.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That if the Magiſtrate doth take upon himſelf that power, we are to be ſo far from complying, as rather, by <hi>Pauls</hi> example, <hi>openly to reprove him;</hi> at leaſt we are to let him know, that we ſtand engaged to another Maſter, who hath commanded us to be <hi>free;</hi> and that it is not out of diſobedience to the Magiſtrate, but out of duty to God, if we peaceably aſſert and maintain our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The laſt objection is this, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>3</label> That Chriſtian Liberty conſiſts not in <hi>Freedom of Practiſe,</hi> but in the <hi>Freedom of Judgment:</hi> And therefore many acknowledge, that if theſe doubtful things were ſo impoſed, as that thereby we ſhould be obliged to think them <hi>neceſſary to ſalvation,</hi> then it was our duty not to do them: But ſince they are meerly enjoyned by the Magiſtrate, as things of Outward order, ſo long we may freely do them, and ſtill retain our Liberty of Conſcience. And this is the Summe of what many Learned men, both in their Writings and Diſcourſes do affirm. But I Anſwer:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Diſtinction is meerly coyned to ſerve a turn, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54584:11"/>the leaſt Foundation, either in <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For, 1. It is not grounded on <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſince all thoſe places wherein we are commanded <hi>not to be the Servants of men, to ſtand faſt in our Liberty,</hi> and the like, do principally reſpect the freedom of our Practiſe, in reference to the Impoſer, whom we ought not to ſubmit unto. Neither, 2. Is there any colour of Reaſon for it; for <hi>Liberty of Judgment,</hi> without <hi>Liberty of Practiſe</hi> ſutable to that Judgment, is not only a vain and ludicrous, but a burdenſom and vexatious thing; and eſpecially in the Service of God, while we alwaies out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly do that, which inwardly we do not approve, is nothing elſe but direct Hypocriſie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Queſtion is not, Whether any may impoſe upon our Judgments; which it is evident none can; but whether our Practiſe, ought not to be left as free as our Judgments, in thoſe things which in reference to his own Worſhip, God himſelf hath not determined. The Diſtinction therefore which ſuppoſes, that our Practiſe may be bound up, and yet our Liberty, which Chriſt and his Apoſtles were ſo tender of, preſerved, doth not prove, but only begs the Queſtion: And like ſuch kind of ſtuffe, is meerly ſo much duſt thrown into our eyes, that we might not read, and make uſe of our Royal Charter.</p>
            <p>I conclude therefore, 1. Since <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> is entirely and indiſpenſably to be preſerved, becauſe the ſame Authority which forbids Murder, doth command that, and it is the Authority of our Law giver, which gives each Law its Sanction. 2. Since <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty</hi> hath place only in the uſe of Indifferent, or forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of doubtful things (for things neceſſary are already enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God, whom we are to obey, whether the Magiſtrate do command them or not) therefore it follows, 1. That whoever takes away the liberty of Practiſe from us, directly contradicts ſo many places of Scripture, which do expreſly enjoyn it: and then, 2. We cannot without diſhonour to God, and violation of one of the greateſt outward Priviledges that the Goſpel doth indulge us, conſent to, or by our Practiſe ſeem to approve of any thing which doth ſo immediatly intrench upon our Chriſtian Freedom: Which is my Second Argument.</p>
            <p>The Third Argument ſhall be taken from the Nature of the things Impoſed, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3</label> which are not purely and in their own Nature <hi>Indifferent;</hi> for then we need not, and I believe, few would ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54584:11"/>at the practiſe of them) but, as I ſtated above, they are things very <hi>doubtful</hi> and <hi>diſputable,</hi> and therefore no Command can make them <hi>Lawful.</hi> For to inſtance only in one of them, and that is, the <hi>Croſſe in Baptiſm,</hi> I may affirm of that, which I find the Learned <hi>Hales</hi> aſſerting concerning <hi>Images.</hi> 1. <hi>It is a thing acknowledged by all, that it is unneceſſary.</hi> 2. <hi>By moſt,</hi> at leaſt in this Nation, <hi>it is ſuſpected.</hi> 3. <hi>By many it is held utterly unlawful: Can then the enjoyning of ſuch a thing, be ought elſe but Abuſe? Or can the Refuſal of</hi> (he ſayes, <hi>Communion,</hi> I ſay) <hi>Submiſſion, be ought elſe but Duty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that many ſpecious Arguments are brought for ſome of our <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> as particularly, for <hi>Set Forms of Prayer,</hi> and for <hi>kneeling at the Sacrament</hi> which, becauſe they are obvious, I ſhall not inſiſt upon: For allowing, but not grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the utmoſt of what is ſaid, that to pray by a Book, is a more rational and Compoſed way of Divine Worſhip, then to pray from the ſtrength of ones own Meditation, and the Aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit; who, becauſe of thoſe Enlargements and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings he gives, is peculiarly ſtiled <hi>the Spirit of Prayer.</hi> 2. Grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>to kneel,</hi> is a more humble, and therefore a more decent Poſture, at the Sacrament, then to <hi>ſit,</hi> as our Saviour and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did; (whoſe Example ſure we may follow without ſin) or at leaſt, <hi>to ſtand,</hi> which is a poſture of Prayer, and therefore of Reverence, and leſſe ſubject to harden the Papiſts, who have ſo monſtrouſly abuſed <hi>Kneeling,</hi> by their Idolatry: But granting the Decency and Conveniency of both, yet,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Since they are either Parts of, or Additions to Divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, unwarrantably deviſed, and forcibly obtruded.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Since the Impoſers do lay ſo much ſtreſſe upon them, that, it is evident, though they call them <hi>Indifferent,</hi> yet they think them <hi>Neceſſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Since in theſe Forms of Prayers, there are thoſe Mixtures, which make our Liturgy, though not ſimply unlawful, yet high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly queſtionable.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Since they are joyned with ſome other Ceremonies, as the <hi>Croſſe in Baptiſme,</hi> which are of a more doubtful Nature.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Since many, as ſober and as Pious Chriſtians, as any are in our Nation, are infinitely grieved at the uſe of them, and are upon the point of forſaking our Aſſemblies, becauſe of them. It followes hence,</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54584:12"/>
            <p n="1">1. That it doth not at all become the Piety and Prudence of Chriſtian Governours to impoſe theſe things which grieve and diſturb very many, and in their own nature are grateful to very few? beſides ſuch who make uſe of their Conformity, as the way to Preferment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That no Conſcientious Miniſter, ſo far as I yet ſee, can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally bear a part in all theſe Ceremonies, becauſe he cannot act in Faith, as doing that, 1. Which God requires not. 2. Which his, perhaps weak, but yet Chriſtian Brother, takes offence at, and if the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>he would never eat meat</hi> (which is alwaies lawful, and to ſome tempers neceſſary Food) <hi>rather then offend his Brother,</hi> ſure he would have forborn a <hi>Croſs,</hi> or a <hi>Surplice</hi> much more.</p>
            <p>If any Anſwer, as ſome do, that it is <hi>Scandalum acceptum &amp; non datum,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> i.e. <hi>an Offence only peeviſhly taken, but not juſtly given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> It is <hi>Scandalum datum, an Offence juſtly given:</hi> For he that upon any pretence whatever, doth conſent, not only to quit his own Liberty, but likewiſe in ſo doing, doth violate and injure the Conſcience of another; he gives juſt occaſion to have his action cenſured, as if he <hi>choſe ſin rather then Affliction,</hi> ſince they are only Motives of Convenience, which ſeem to lie at the bottom, and make him ſtoop to ſo mean a Bondage.</p>
            <p>Some object, That it is true, by doing theſe things, we offend our Brother, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> but then by refuſing, we ſhould offend the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, who is ſomthing more then our Brother, to whom we owe not only the duty of Love, but likewiſe of Subjection; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the leſs Offence muſt give place to the greater. But I anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> That if the Magiſtrate hath no power to impoſe, as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready proved, then he hath no reaſon to be offended at my refuſal to obey him; ſince <hi>eatenus jus non habet,</hi> and therefore I ſhould more <hi>ſcandalize, i. e.</hi> give him a greater occaſion of ſinning, by ſubmitting to, then by quiet diſowning of his Authority. For by ſubmitting, I ſhall beget this Opinion in him, that he doth well to impoſe, which is undoubtedly ſinful; whereas by diſowning his Authority, I only make my ſelf liable to ſuffering, which every good Chriſtian ought at all times to be prepared for.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our Saviour hath already taught us how little we are to care for the offence which men take at that ſober and juſt uſe which we make of our Liberty: For when he refuſed <hi>to waſh his hands before
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54584:12"/>meat,</hi> (which by the way, was a Rite much more innocent, then thoſe I now diſpute of) and gave this for his ground, that it <hi>was a plant not of his Fathers planting;</hi> his Diſciples ſeem to impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune him to condeſcend unto the Phariſees, who were his law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Governours, by urging, that <hi>they were offended at his Saying:</hi> But our Saviour in ſtead of aſſenting, cries out, <hi>let them alone, they are Blind Guides,</hi> with other words, ſhewing, that while they made uſe of their Authority, to preſs ſuch needleſs Toyes, it was his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to diſobey them. Which carriage of our Saviour is ſo much the more remarkable, in that, when they came to demand Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute-money, though he alledged, that by his Birthright he was free from any ſuch Tax, yet, ſaith he, <hi>rather then offend them,</hi> let us pay it; plainly implying, that in Civil things, not to ſtand too nicely upon our terms, but for peace ſake even to part with ſome of our Right, is honeſt and commendable; but in Religious things we muſt not yield a tittle, becauſe in them, the honour of God is immediatly concerned: For, as being Lord of the Conſcience, and ſole Dictator of what way he will be ſerved in, he expects, we ſhould upon all occaſions, openly aſſert his Right, and neither <hi>teach for Doctrine,</hi> nor ſolemnize for Worſhip, <hi>the Commandments of men.</hi> For, that I may obviate an Exception of ſome, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that theſe things are not impoſed as Doctrines: When a Ceremony comes to be urged and preſſed, beyond the bounds of a thing Indifferent, here though no Doctrine be mentioned, yet there is a Doctrine couched under it, and that is, this which I have been all this while ſpeaking againſt, <hi>That the Magistrate hath power to impoſe in Religious Worſhip.</hi> So that when things doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful come upon that ſcore to be obtruded, we muſt reſolutely refuſe to do them, leſt we ſhould ſeem to own and aſſent unto the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> To conclude therefore, Since the things in queſtion, are ſo preſſed, as if the Impoſers thought them neceſſary. 2. Since many of them are very diſputable. 3. Since moſt of them are very ſcandalous and offenſive to our weaker Brethren, it followes, that they are not in their own nature Indifferent, and therefore it cannot be lawful to practiſe them. And ſo much for the Third Argument.</p>
            <p>The Fourth and laſt Argument ſhall be taken from the Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance and Correſpondency which theſe things have to others, which we have already renounced in the Popiſh worſhip; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54584:13"/>from the impoſſibility, that any rational or ſober account can be given why we diſſent from thoſe, if we aſſent to theſe. For, I would fain know, wherein lies the true ground of our ſeparation from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> if not in this, becauſe they obtrude ſuch conditions of Communion, which Gods Word doth not warrant us to aſſent to? For let men ſpeak as much as they pleaſe againſt <hi>Images, Crucifixes, Praying to Saints,</hi> or for <hi>the Dead,</hi> &amp;c. at laſt it will be found, that the only firm and ſolid Argument to overthrow all theſe things, is this, <hi>They are not written.</hi> God hath no where in his Word commanded ſuch things, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may ſafely reject them. But on the ſame ſcore, the <hi>Croſs,</hi> the <hi>Surplice, Bowing Kneeling,</hi> and the reſt, muſt be rejected too, as being equally uncommanded,: For how can we ſatisfie any inquiſitive man, why in Baptiſm, we have caſt off <hi>Oyle,</hi> and retain the <hi>Croſs?</hi> why in the other Sacrament, we retain <hi>Kneeling,</hi> and refuſe <hi>Adoration?</hi> Why we bow to the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and yet are offended at a <hi>Crucifix?</hi> In ſhort, why we have pared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſome Rites, either as <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> or elſe as <hi>ſuperfluous,</hi> and yet have retained others, that are equally ſcandalous, equally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defenſible? If we anſwer, that we did it, becauſe <hi>every Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Church hath power to judge of Ceremonies,</hi> and to impoſe upon her Subjects, as few or as many as ſhe thinks fit; Will it not ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably follow, that our Church may when ſhe pleaſes, bring in all thoſe exploded Rites upon us, and when ſhe doth ſo, we are bound to ſubmit unto her Authority? So that all the advantage we have got by our Reformation (which at the beginning of it, was the beſt and the moſt ſtupendious that ever the world ſaw) is only this, that we have lopt off ſome Branches of Popery, but left the Root untouched; as owning that Doctrine of Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which may whenever the Magiſtrate pleaſes, bring in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward practiſe of that Religion again upon us. I do not ſpeak this, as if I did in the leaſt imagine, that our Governours do ſo much as dream of any ſuch thing, but I argue meerly as a rational man, and conſidering the nature of things; for ſince every man then acts rationally, when he acts conformably to the Principle he holds; therefore he that firſt miſtakes things <hi>doubtful,</hi> for things <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> and then maintains, that the Magiſtrate hath power to make even things Doubtful, Neceſſary, when he impoſes them; he leaves the Magiſtrate free, to bring in as much of the <hi>Popiſh Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:54584:13"/>as he is pleaſed to think is either decent or convenient.</p>
            <p>Since then the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> the <hi>Surplice,</hi> &amp;c. are all of the ſame Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Nature and Original, with other parts of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which we have worthily rejected, as being coyned in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licenſed Mint of mens Brain, without the ſtamp of Divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; it followes, that either we muſt not uſe them, or elſe we muſt acknowledge, that if <hi>Oyl for Infants, Holy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction for the ſick, Exorciſmes,</hi> &amp;c. were enjoyned, we could lawfully ſubmit to them too, and ſo never fix our ſelves a certain point of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Practiſe, but depend altogether upon the Beck and Pleaſure of our Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>Againſt this, I know not what can be objected, except as ſome affirm, that <hi>the Pope is not Antichriſt,</hi> ſo others will take upon them to prove that <hi>Popery</hi> is not <hi>Idolatry.</hi> If any Proteſtant be of that mind, I hope he thinks of returning ſpeedily to their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but till I underſtand, how <hi>Pictures may be made and placed, if not as Objects, yet as Helps of Devotion; how Saints can firſt be Canonized, and then prayed to, how the Bread can be confined to a place, and yet adored as god, how the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>beſides being pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, can be entreated to command her Son;</hi> till I ſay, I underſtand how theſe, and many more ſuch things can be done, and no <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> committed, I muſt take leave to affirm, that if that <hi>Church</hi> be not <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> there never was, nor can be ſuch a thing as <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> in the World.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore, I will acknowledge, that <hi>uſing the Croſs,</hi> though not in Baptiſm, is very ancient, and mentioned more then once by <hi>Tertullian</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Apolog.</note>, that a peculiar Reverence to the <hi>Name of Jeſus,</hi> is aſſerted by <hi>Origen</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Lib. adv. Celſ.</note>, that the <hi>Worſhip of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> or ſomthing very like it, is maintained by <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apolog.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Prayer for the Dead,</hi> as I remember, by <hi>Cyprian,</hi> I am ſure by <hi>Tertullian</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Apolog.</note>, <hi>Purgatory</hi> by <hi>Arnobius,</hi> &amp;c. But yet theſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which in thoſe Excellent Writers (who were newly reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered out of <hi>Gentiliſme</hi>) were very tolerable Miſtakes and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, did neither hurt them, nor the Church of Chriſt, till the world was grown lazy enough to believe, and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had force enough to impoſe them, as Neceſſary Doctrines. This is that which not only diffuſed, but ſo far fixed the fatal Poyſon of Errour, that the world can never expect to be freed, till it pleaſes God to raiſe up ſome generous and truly Heroick Prince,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54584:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>who may be convinced of the truth of Chriſtian Religion, not by hear-ſay from others, but by a through ſearch and enquiry into the Cauſes of it himſelf, and growing from thence aſſured, that nothing can more hinder the Progreſs of the Goſpel, then to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe and alter its ſimplicity (for a ſtrange dreſs muſt needs ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſuſpected) will reſolve to give it a free and undiſturbed Paſſage, and never draw his Sword, but when Malice and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance do joyn together, not only to oppoſe, but to perſecute it; how will Truth then, being unfettered and ſet free, from the Clogges of pretended <hi>Decency,</hi> but indeed Antichriſtian Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, run through this Nation, and chaſe Errour before it, as the Light doth Darkneſs? This Great and Glorious work I dare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt prophecy that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> is reſerved for, whoſe pious and unequalled <hi>Declaration,</hi> hath already indulged as much Liberty, as any ſober-minded Chriſtian can pretend to: and which will then undoubtedly be made a Law, when by our conſtant and chearful Sufferings for this Doctrine of <hi>Liberty,</hi> we have expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and waſhed away thoſe Scandals, which our many odious and unparallel'd Abuſes have caſt upon it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
